Artur Schaefer

Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais, Brazil



artur.schaefer2@gmail.com



linkedin.com/in/artur-schaefer

Summary

As a senior developer, I've been working with Android for over 4 years, focused on Kotlin and Java as the main programming languages. Also, I'm a Flutter enthusiast and enjoy the framework and how easy it is to do applications. Work in a broad range of projects, including mobility, social media, real estate properties, and finance. Some of the projects were built from scratch but others have over 50 million users.

The technical background was provided by a Bachelor's Degree in Information Systems, finished in June 2018. While doing the Bachelor's Degree, I was doing an Android Developer Nanodegree from Udacity, which I finished in October 2018. In this course, I was introduced to the best practice of Android and the new Jetpack Architecture Components. In that year Java was the main language for Android applications, but I started to use Kotlin.

My current responsibility in the technical aspect is to ensure the user's security while using the application. To this goal, my team provides tools to users to validate themselves in a new device using photos, like Selfie or documents, or SMS/email. Another library is to reset the password. In this flow, it's also possible to use Selfie and documents to validate the user's identity, but in this case, it is possible to change the user's data.

I'm not just a coder so, in the work, I also mentor my fellows with less experience or with doubts. Proposing improvements to the whole project it's part of my daily basis. Code reviews are part of my duty as a developer too, and by doing this it's possible to share more knowledge with our team.

Experience



Android Developer

PicPay

Oct 2020 - Present (9 months +)

- Mobile developer using Kotlin and Java for Android Applications
- · Focus on security and access app
- Kanban as Agile Methodology
- Built code with SOLID, Clean Architecture, and MVVM
- Use tools like RxJava, Koin, Espresso, JUnit, Android Jetpack, Biometrics, Firebase ML Kit, and others

b Developer

Hotmart

Aug 2019 - Oct 2020 (1 year 3 months)

- · Android development, using Kotlin / Java, in a multidisciplinary team
- The app, Sparkle, had more than 1 million downloads on the Google Play Store
- In the application I handled with creation and consumption of media (Videos, Audios, Photos, PDF, and texts).
- The two biggest challenges faced were: redoing the flow of content consumption and increasing the health of the application, reducing crashes, and improving user usability.

- Main architecture design used: MVVM + Clean Architecture
- The most used tools/libraries: ExoPlayer, FFMpeg, DownloadManager, WorkManager, Room, CameraX (and other camera APIs)

Android Developer

Usemobile

Sep 2018 - Aug 2019 (1 year)

- Part of the Android application development team, using Kotlin and Java in all projects.
- Use of current architecture patterns, such as MVP, MVVM, and VIPER.
- Use of agile methodologies SCRUM, XP (Extreme Programming) during the development process.
- Handling of information from servers through APIs.
- Experience in using Google APIs including Firebase (Realtime database, notifications, Crashlytics, Login, Events), Google Places, and Google Vision.

Information Technology Support Assistant

Synergia Consultoria Socioambiental

Jan 2017 - Aug 2018 (1 year 8 months)

- Performed technology support activities, involving systems and network infrastructure, data analysis, as well as filtering for consistency of information collected through field activities.
- Development of applications to support various activities, using technologies such as VBA, Java, PHP, MySQL, and PostgreSQL.



Volunteer Researcher

CNPq

Jul 2016 - Jun 2017 (1 year)

- Developing a work plan for the application and assessment of modeling services using archimate in actual cloud-services scenarios.
- Results were presented at the 1st IFES Integration Day, in October 2017 at Campus Colatina.
- The research was carried out while a student at the Instituto Federal Espírito Santo Campus Colatina.

Programming class monitor

Ifes - Instituto Federal do Espírito Santo

Jul 2016 - Dec 2016 (6 months)

- Supported students in technology courses programming topics at IFES Campus Colatina. Helping Bachelor of Information Systems, and Integrated Computer Technician students.
- The languages I worked with during this period were mainly Python, C / C ++, and Java. HTML, Javascript, and PHP were occasionally requested and were also worked on during the period.



📵 Undergraduate Research Assistant

CNPa

Jan 2015 - Jan 2016 (1 year 1 month)

• Work period related to the technological initiation project "Educational robotics for learning to program", seeking to encourage the learning of programming for students inside the campus.

- The work was carried out on the Instituto Federal do Espírito Santo Campus Colatina, and during the period in which I was a student in the Bachelor of Information Systems course.
- For participation in robotics competitions/tournaments, the Asimov team was founded. Among the competitions, we participated in Brazilian and Latin American competitions.

Education

Udacity Brasil

Android Developer Nanodegree, Development of mobile applications 2018 - 2018

- Created in partnership with Google, this course taught me to use various tools, principles, and standards that support the development of Android.
- During the course, 7 projects were sent using various tools and techniques, such as SQLite, Firebase Database, Firebase Storage, Firebase Cloud Message, Asynctask, Loaders, Picasso, Glide, Retrofit, Volley, Content Providers, Home Screen Widgets, Gradle, Material Design, Architecture Components...

Ifes - Instituto Federal do Espírito Santo

Bachelor's degree, Information Technology 2014 - 2018

- Graduation allowed me to acquire knowledge in several areas, from programming to administration disciplines. While in graduation I participated in two research projects and was a monitor of the course's programming.
- Regarding programming, I saw the following languages and tools during the course: C / C ++, Java, PHP, HTML, CSS, Java for Android, Java ServerPages, MySQL, MongoDB.
- Course description according to the institution: The Bachelor of Information Systems course aims to train professionals to develop, implement and manage an information technology infrastructure, data, and systems that cover the entire organization.

Licenses & Certifications

- Android Developer Nanodegree
- The Complete Android Kotlin Developer Course Udemy Brasil
- Aprenda Design Patterns com SOLID Udemy Brasil
- **Application security** Alura

Skills

Java • Kotlin • Scrum • Agile Methodologies • Algorithms • Mobile Application Development • Android Development • Object-Oriented Programming (OOP)

Honors & Awards

- 3rd PLACE in category IEEE Standard Educational Kit (SEK) at LARC/CBR (Competição Latino Americana e Brasileira de Robótica), IEEE SEK. IEEE Nov 2015
- 4rd place in at TRUFES (Torneio de Robótica da UFES) UFES Sep 2015